this is a big problem it's a really big
problem I see it a lot in my patients
with PCOS or patients with uterine
fibroid these chemicals are influencing
the behavior of estrogen sensitive
tissue and uterine fibroids have tons of
estrogen receptors so you want to make
sure that as part of the treatment and
getting that person better is to reduce
their exposure to these environmental
estrogens and and this is really the why
so I'm going to talk about the
environmental impact on our you know on
chronic disease so Lincoln environmental
exposure to toxicant and chronic so this
is what we're covering today and um in
subsequent meetings so the World Health
Organization made a a comment stating
escalating rates of
neurocognitive metabolic autoimmune and
cardiovascular disease diseases cannot
be ascribed only to genetics lifestyle
and n and nutrition early life and
ongoing exposures and bioaccumulated
toxicant may also cause chronic disease
and what I do when I see patients I
often Times review their environmental
exposures because we're living in a
toxic soup of chemicals we're exposed to
so much everywhere from what we eat what
we put on our bodies what we're
breathing is just everywhere chemicals
are ubiquitous in the environment and
there's more and more studies coming out
showing the um impact that these
toxicant have on our our
physiology so it's really important for
clinicians to consider the environmental
aspects of health so these are just
examples of some toxicant and there's a
difference between Toxin and toxin often
people use the word toxins loosely but
that's referencing an endogenous
production of a toxin in something made
in the body internally toxicant are more
man-made so we're talking about
pesticides insecticides we all know
tobacco is it's not healthy so these are
some examples of toxicant that we're
exposed to heavy metals I often work
with patients who either in construction
or firefighters or painters and often
times I see a lot of lead and cadmium in
these patients and so it this is
something that accumulates based on
occupational exposures and just being in
a world of soup chemicals is just what
you're going to find and so heavy metals
pesticides disinfectants mod is a big
one it's a biotoxin I work with patients
with mod and and 70% of us homes have
mod and no one knows it and so you have
to be considering mold it as part of
your differential if a person has
respiratory symptoms or they have these
chronic infections they can't really
figure out what's going on and all of
their labs are normal and they the
doctors can't figure it out you go in
get pulmonary testing and they say well
we can't figure out it's not asthma we
don't know what it is oftentimes it's
mold so there are other toxicants you
know OCC from occupational exposures
Plastics rubbers you know perfumes to
personal uh body personal care products
that we're using on our skin so women
leave the home with over 500 different
chemicals every day from the hairsprays
and Etc dyes and so there there's a lot
that we're been exposed to and and it
does impact our health so when we're
exposed to these chemicals they have the
ability to impact multiple organ systems
obesity influenc in metabolism lipid and
glucose metabolism creating weight gain
um diabetes just the endocrine system um
pulmonary system the central nervous
system it goes on the gut uh these
chemicals can um impact they directly
interact with different systems of
dividing can cause pathology this is
interesting this was an an issue from
nature earlier this year tumor promotion
air pollution drives lung cancer and
nonsmokers how many of you know
it's someone who's had lung cancer but
know history of smoking I personally
know people who've developed lung cancer
and had no history of smoking and often
times people think oh just because
you're smoke you you're going to get
lung cancer or if you have lung cancer
you you must have been a smoker that's
not
true that's not true at all in fact they
say here air pollution is associated
with the development of lung cancer
cancer um analysis of clinical samples
and mouse cancer models suggest that
inflammation and a tumor promotion
process induced by polluted air are the
major culprits the World Health
Organization um has concluded that this
dangerous trajectory has resulted in an
increased risk of lung cancer with an
estimated 250,000 worldwide deaths per
year attributable to atmospheric
pollution okay so this is a real issue I
like I said I work with patients with
lung cancer and it's sad because
oftentimes these patients are young in
their early 30s and they have advanced
disease metastatic disease
unfortunately so here are two proposed
hypotheses excuse me as to the
development of Genesis of the lung so in
the first model we have a lung cell and
there's a mutation that happens as a a
result of exposure to an environmental
toxic in air and then it promotes
changes at a cellular level and then it
promotes the development of a benign
tumor and when the conditions are right
that benign tumor will become develop
invasive properties and that will lead
into a fully malignant cancer by the
time a person gets their lung cancer
diagnosis is already late stage and have
already metastasized think about 10% of
it has already metastasized to the brain
so it's one of those cancers you have to
catch early um and if there's a family
history any cancer you really want to be
ahead of the cancer your the cancer
diagnosis if you can with utilizing
early cancer detection technology and
the next model here and letter B there's
some underlining mutations that what
they proposed there's underlining
mutations in these can these cells of
the lungs and when the conditions are
right when there's some kind of
environmental insult from like a
polluted toxin toxicant from the air
come in contact with an existing t or
cell that already has mutations it will
mount an inflammatory response the
macras or white blood cells release the
cyto coses that create all kinds of
inflammation and that will promote the
formation of a tumor and then the lid
that keeps going on and on and develops
into excuse me a tumor that has invasive
properties and there you have it a lung
cancer so there these are two in my
opinion good um models for at least
hypotheses and explaining the
underlining mechanism as to how air
pollution is driving lung cancer but
what they both have in common is that
air pollution is a driving Factor so
when I work with anyone with chronic
disease or lung or any kind of cancer
any kind of solid tumor cancer there's
always a driving mechanism and
environment is one of them and we have
to look at this because when people have
chronic disease and when they have
cancer it's usually multifactoral and
because it's multifactoral it means
there needs to be a multifactoral
approach to investigation and really
looking at the underlying drivers um to
the Pathology and environmental medicine
is one of them so this is interesting
this is a review looking at how
endocrine disrupting effects of BPA so
we've all heard of BPA but there's many
different types of bisphenols and this
is looking at the impact of BPA on
cardiovascular health and what they
found is that their findings suggest
that BPA and pairs so they were looking
at the mechanism how is BPA exposure
increasing the risk for cardiovascular
disease and risk factors our findings
suggest that BPA impairs cardiac
excitability through intracellular
mechanisms involving an inhibition of
main ion channels changes in calcium so
calcium is a very important ion for the
cardiac tissue and so BPA can impair
that process and induction of oxidative
stress and epigenetic modification so we
have an epig genome which is our
environment our lifestyle factors our
dietary factors behavioral practices can
influence the IG genome these are genes
that are influenced by lifestyle and
dietary practices and BPA can facilitate
that change our data support that BPA
exposure increases the risk of
developing cardiovascular diseases and
included atherosclerosis and its risk
factors such as hypertension and um
diabetes furthermore BPA exposure is
also particularly harmful in pregnancy
promoting the development of
hypertensive disorders during pregnancy
in summary BPA exposure com um comprises
human health or compromises human health
promoting a development and progression
of cardiovascular disease and risk
factors
so don't have any it try to reduce your
exposure to BPA and you can sweat BPA
out that's what this is all about when
we say detox you can actually sweat it
out and also reduce your exposure and
we'll talk about how to do that in um
subsequent
presentations this was a um statement
from the American Heart Association they
understand that obesity is multifactoral
in complex and therefore must be
addressed on a on multiple levels and
endocrine disrupting chemicals such as
diyl sterol which is synthetic estrogen
bisphenol a phalates or ganons have been
proposed as potential obesogens now
obesogens are chemicals that can promote
obesity okay they contribute to a toxic
chemical burden that may initiate or
exaggerate the development of obesity
and its related comorbidities okay and
these chemicals endocrine disrupting
chemicals are found and Plastics
Cosmetics shampoos soaps lubricants and
I don't want to overwhelm you all
because it can be overwhelming it's like
oh my goodness there's just chemicals
everywhere I can't get rid of them but
there's some things that you can do to
reduce your
exposure so the endocrine society says
when endocrine disrupting chemicals
block connections between hormones and
their receptors they reprogram the parts
of the immune the endocrine system that
govern metabolism energy balance and
appetite endocrine disrupting chemicals
change the sensitivity to glucose and
Metabolism of lipids all of this PR
predisposes a person to gain weight okay
so they've done studies um in animals
and what was interesting is that as
we're seeing obesity just continues to
climb in humans they're actually seeing
the same phenomena in animals animals
are gaining weight too and it's because
of the
chemicals as I mentioned BPA is just one
type of bisphenol we have bpb bisphenol
c bisphenol s so just an FYI if you see
anything that's said we'll talk about
this later and we'll give you all an
opportunity to talk about this but when
you see things that say BPA free that's
not excluding the other BPA the other
bisphenols so there's other types of
bisphenols as we're seeing here and this
is just showing this is a schematic just
showing you know what role does it have
at a cellular level so when we think of
disease it really starts at a very
fundamental level in our cells there's a
lot going on so BPA has the ability to
bind to receptors and these receptors
once they're activated they can send
signals within the cell and alter intra
C proteins that as we see here the irs1
and the akt they're down regulated or
upregulated in ways that will influence
metabolism it can downregulate BPA um
bind into receptors can actually
downregulate mitochondrial function
mitochondrial dysfunction can lead to a
many types of sorry I got to pop up
here um mitochondrial dysfun function
can affect so many different things
that's a whole different subject but BPA
has the ability to directly influence
mitochondrial function and affect how
energy production of the cell is carried
out and then because of the
intracellular proteins that are being
downregulated because of BPA exposure it
does influence glucose uptake it down
regulates glucose uptake in the cell and
this is what's happening at a cellular
level this is what happens when we're
exposed to BPA or if we're exposed to
other environmental toxicant this is the
direct mechanism it's directly
influencing how the cell behaves binding
into receptors and influencing the
intracellular physiology and this is
what's creating weight gain and
promoting diabetes so this is different
aspects of how BPA can influence
different parts of complications of
diabetes diabetic cognitive dysfunction
this can BPA can influence that by
downregulating the insulin receptivity
inside the brain promoting nerve damage
affects the kidneys as well and
affecting the filtering units of the
kidneys and creating scarring it also
affects the pancreas and down regulates
the production of insulin and it affects
the lipid metabolism effect in
cardiovascular health the list goes on
BPA has this is just one example I I'm
just mentioning one example there's just
so many different toxicants and I would
if I were to talk about everything you
guys will be here all day this is just
an example of BPA and how it it's its
role in influencing different parts of
the disease process of a person with
diabetes um when we're exposed to
toxicant at the recept level it affects
how the um intracellular mechanisms are
are performing inside a cell and that
ultimately changes the behavior at a
cell now once in a Cell the uh BPA or
any kind of chemical have the ability to
affect our genomics our DNA so it
promotes genomics instability these
these chemicals either radiation or
combustion products from Auto exhaust or
even d di AR of the things that we're
consuming it has the ability to create
breaks in a DNA or create add-ons to our
DNA that aren't supposed to be there and
what happens is it causes the DNA
material or genetic material that Reg
you know is responsible for everything
that goes on in our body when it's
mutations at that level when there's
damage to our DNA that promotes disease
if the conditions are right and there's
a lot of other things going on it just
might actually Express you know Express
proteins that can actually be be
responsible for creating disease so we
want to protect our DNA and
unfortunately the environmental
toxicants that we're exposed to damage
our DNA and and one example dietarily
what I you know I've talked about before
heterocyclic amans you know when you're
frying red meat they release these
carcinogens they're very mutogenic and
they have the ability to change and
alter our DNA and promote genomic
instability we don't want that so I have
a question for you do you currently take
active steps to reduce your toxic
exposure a no because I was not aware of
the dangers of environmental toxins B
yes I make efforts daily to avoid
environmental toxicant that's what it is
or see sometimes well for those who are
learning this for the first time and
learning the role that environment plays
in health stay tuned because there's a
lot more that we're going to
cover so the environmental uh Protection
Agency dis defines what an endocrine
disrupting chemical is so I mentioned
BPA but there's so many other types of
endocrine disrupting chemicals like
thades and they're defined as an
exogenous agent that interferes with the
synthesis
secretion transport binding action or
elimination of natural hormones so let
me explain this when your body so I'll
just use the ovaries I mean we have
different endocrine systems but your
ovaries pump out estrogen progesterone
your adrenals pump out cortisol whenever
a a tissue produces a hormone that
hormone needs to to be secreted and
transported by binding proteins to their
the local tissues that the target tissue
that required those hormones and they
bind the hormones bind to receptors and
then once they bind to receptor they
they promote the facilitate these
intracellular U mechanisms to Dy the
action noes but they have a half life
the hormones have a half life and they
have to be eliminated and what they're
saying is if there's any hor synthetic
hormone or something that's not made by
the body comes in and it interferes with
that entire process then work that's an
endocrine disrupting chemical because
it's interfering with how your endocrine
system functions and and so if it
affects the elimination natural hormones
in a body which are responsible these
hormones are responsible for the
maintenance or homeostasis balance okay
reproduction and their regulation of
Developmental processes these hormones
synthetic hormones have the ability to
impact virtually all aspects of hormone
physiology and this is a bad theme this
is just a summary of the 10 different
ways and some of the chemicals that can
actually facilitate disrupting the
endocrine system either from hormone
distribution or breakdown or even
hormone transport like BPA fungoides
BCBS hormone synthesis adrine oh that's
interesting we're going to talk about
that one our per chlorates salades and
perfumes ladies you like perfumes or you
know Plastics they have the ability to
impact hormone synthesis and so this I'm
not going to go through this whole list
here here but these are the various
different types of endocrine disrupting
chemicals that can affect how a hormone
behaves in your body and so the the
easiest way to say I can say this
because some of us are Christian but
it's a counterfeit hormone like it it's
it mimics what your body naturally
produces and it's it's a counterfeit we
know the devil's into counterfeit this
is what happens in our body when we're
exposed to these environmental toxic
and here's an example I'm just going to
hone in on this if you look here at
BPA look at the left and you see signal
in systems affected by BPA so thyroid
signaling look at this the BPA is able
to bind to thy thyroid receptors and
then bind to receptors that promote fat
accumulation lipid accumulation and
promoting obesity estrogen signaling yes
BPA can impact estrogen signaling so all
of my breast cancer patients what do I
do I have to reduce their exposure to ex
exogenous sources of estrogen okay and
BPA is one of them okay Androgen
signaling glucocorticoid signaling
because BPA has the ability to lock in
on these receptors and influence these
different cell types if you look on the
right you see 17 beta estrodial this is
the biological form of estral and we see
bisphenol a if you look here at the blue
highlighted region this is a
hydroxyphenol group if you see the
backbone structure of estral that's made
in a woman's body is actually similar to
the backbone structure of the BPA so
what do you think is going to happen
here BPA is able to bind two estrogen
receptors imagine a a lock in a key and
you put in the key and the key how many
of you I know you noticed you put in the
key the wrong key but it fits into the
lock but it's not the right key so it
doesn't open so it's kind of like that
with these chemicals they can bind but
they actually do have the ability to and
yes who's
talking they actually have the ability
to influence the behavior of that cell
and and exert their effects in a way
that are is
unfavorable of course if it's an
estrogen receptor we don't want to have
constant signaling of of estrogen
receptor to promote uh proliferation um
unwanted proliferation of breast tissue
or uterine tissue in women who have
uterine fibroid for example this is a
big problem it's a really big problem I
see it a lot in my patients with PCOS or
patients with uterine fibroid these
these chemicals are influencing the
behavior of estrogen sensitive tissue
and uterine fibroids have tons of
estrogen receptors so you want to make
sure that as part of the treatment and
getting that person better is to reduce
their exposure to these environmental
estrogens so here's another one this is
structure of thyroid hormone same thing
applies to my thyroid patients I have to
reduce your exposure to exogenous
sources of hormones because the thyroid
is a gland that re redu it uh produces
hormones
and so if you see here in letter A T3
hormone okay um thyroid produces 80% T4
and it converts into T3 and that's the
biological form that the tissues use and
is also converted in other tissues if
you look here at B and C and D these are
different bisphenols so you have BPA you
have BPS and BPF you see the structure
there they both had those hydroxy groups
and it matches the hydroxy group on the
structure of T3 and so this is why if
you have a thyroid problem you want to
reduce your exposure to these
environmental endocrine disrupting
chemicals because they will indefinitely
will block the The receptors and and try
to mimic what the thyroid would do and
that's you know you don't want that and
that can either lead to an up regulation
or down regulation hypo or hypo hyper
hypo thyroid condition so this is a
problem and it's something that
definitely should be considered so
atrazine we talked about not just a
couple of side slides this blew me away
so listen look at this atrazine so they
were this is a study from UC Berkeley
Cal Berkeley and they were looking at
the role of atrazine which is as a
pesticide and they spray it on corn they
spray it on crops it's a very common
pesticide that's used and what they
found when they sprayed frogs male frogs
listen to this atrazine exposed males
were
demasculinized okay chem chemically
castrated and completely feminized as
adults
wow 10% of exposed genetic males
developed into functional
females what do you think is going on
there what's going
on this this is sprayed in the on the
the stuff we
eat okay males that are genetically male
frogs are turning into
females have
mercy these toxic affect the
mitochondria these are the different
parts of the mitochondria and there's we
have to appreciate the mitochondria is
biotransformation our bioenergetics and
how the body produces energy if you feel
like you just don't have your energy
anymore you're always tired this is
where it at this is where it's at the
mitochondria we have to improve
mitochondrial function and improve
adrenal Health the hypothalamic
pituitary adrenal axis cortisol
regulation all of these things was what
you have to look at and is influenced
and impact by environmental toxicant and
the toxicant can affect the electron
trans transport chain is is different
parts of the mitochondria that's
responsible for energy production and so
basically long story short when you're
exposed to toxicants is damaging to the
mitochondria and and that's what's also
responsible for giving people energy and
taking energy away and I won't spend a
whole lot of time on this this is is the
impact that toxicant have on our gut the
gut microbiome is impacted they also
play a role in
biotransformation of toxicant when we're
exposed to something the microbiome
facilitates the metabolism I think it's
about I think it's 75 or 80% microbiome
plays a role in breaking down our
toxicant that we're we're exposed to so
when and but they it also creates
disbiosis it shifts the microbiome in a
way that's not healthy and promotes
intestinal
hyperpermeability and that's never a
good thing because that's been connected
a lot to many different types of the
hundred types of autoimmune disease so
we we have to keep in mind it does
impact the health of the gut the
environmental toxicants that we're
exposed to a scientific World Journal
says intervention to reduce the body
burden of persistent toxicant the field
of clinical
detoxification constitutes a fundamental
and urgently required approach to reduce
intoxicant related health issues this is
what I practice one part of what I
practice I don't detox all of my
patients but I I do utilize it when I do
the testing and I see people are really
toxic and and even if you don't do
testing if you've not done a detox in a
long time you've not had given your body
opportunity to purge and clean stuff out
this is a great opportunity so I have
one more question does your doctor
consider environmental toxin exposure as
part of your medical
history a no I'm never asked about my
environmental exposures B yes my doctor
takes in into account my environmental
toxin exposures well as we can see we
really should be thinking about that
even as patients we should consider you
know no one really thinks about the
toxins in their home and air filters and
you know the indoor air is actually more
toxic than outdoor air and we really
need to think about these things and and
what we're exposing ourselves to okay
genetics lows a gum but environment
pulls a trigger so you have control over
your exposures to some degree from a
dietary perspective from environmental
perspective something just short if
you're at a grocery store don't take the
receipt it's loaded with BPA okay don't
eat from cans you know things of that
nature and they've actually done studies
looking at just making those small
adjustments makes a big impact
significant impact on how much BPA is
actually in your system okay so just
those small ch es can have dramatic
effects on your health